Preliminary Guide to the Duke Memorial Records, 1929 - 1936 UA.01.08.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Memorial records
1929 - 1936
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Memorial
UA.01.08.0001
4 Linear Feet
The Duke Memorial was formed in 1929 to honor Washington, Benjamin N., and James B. Duke. The group worked on several projects, including building the Memorial Chapel in Duke Chapel, financing the purchase of Duke Homestead, and building a statue of James B. Duke. The collection consists mainly of financial documents, as well as general correspondence, minutes, and proposals and suggestions. Major topics include the construction of Memorial Chapel and the sarcophagi within, the purchase of Duke Homestead, and the financing of the James B. Duke Statue. Major correspondents include James A. Thomas, W. W. Flowers, and Alex H. Sands. English.
4000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Duke Memorial Records was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1957 (A56-390).
Historical Note
The Duke Memorial was formed in 1929 to establish a permanent memorial to Washington, James B., and Benjamin N. Duke. Among the projects undertaken by the group were the building of the Memorial Chapel in Duke Chapel, the installation of sarcophagi within Memorial Chapel, the Duke Homestead, and the building of the James B. Duke statue. James A. Thomas appears to have been the moving force behind the formation of the group. From 1929 to the early 1930s, many in North Carolina and across the nation donated money to the Memorial, and became "sponsors" or "subscribers" to the cause. By 1936, the Memorial's main goals had been accomplished, and the Executive Committee reorganized the Memorial as a perpetual trust " to keep in the minds of the public the needs, both financial and otherwise, of Duke University.. ." (Minutes, April 22, 1936).
Collection Overview
The materials within the collection are mainly financial documents, including bank statements, bank reports, bank correspondence, deposit records, account books, check registers, audit reports, and subscriber and sponsor lists and amounts donated. Other materials include general correspondence, minutes, and proposals and suggestions. The main topics within the collection are the raising and disbursement of funds for the Memorial projects, foremost of which was the construction of Memorial Chapel. Major correspondents include James A. Thomas, W. W. Flowers, and Alex H. Sands.
Related Archival Materials note
Horace Trumbauer Architectural Drawings
Duke University Archives
William Preston Few Records
Duke University Archives
Fund raising; Financial records; Duke University. Chapel; Duke Homestead (Durham, N.C.); Duke Memorial; Thomas, J. A. (James Augustus), 1862-1940; Sands, Alexander H., 1891-1960; Duke, Washington, 1820-1905; Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925; Duke, Benjamin N. (Benjamin Newton)
- Accession Number A56-390
  - Audits (Box 1)
  - Audit Report and Certificate [Oversized] (Box 1)
  - Bank Correspondence
    - The Fidelity Bank
      - 1929 (Box 1)
      - 1930 (Box 1)
      - 1931-1932 (Box 1)
      - 1933-1936 (Box 1)
    - Guaranty Trust Co. (Box 1)
  - Bank Deposits, Guaranty Trust Company, 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Bank Deposits, Guaranty Trust Company (Box 1)
  - Bank Statements [Oversized] (Box 1)
  - Bronze Books (Box 1)
  - Check Register (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Constitution and By-Laws (Box 1)
  - Deposit Book (Box 1)
  - Duke Homestead, 1929-1936 (Box 1)
  - File 19D [Correspondence re: finances] (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Reports [and Correspondence] (Box 1)
  - Fund-Raising Proposals (Box 1)
  - General Letters (Box 1)
  - Lists of Sponsors (Box 1)
  - Memoranda, Sketches, Interviews (Box 1)
  - [Memorial Campaign Planning Materials] (Box 1)
  - Minutes (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous [Correspondence], 1929 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous [Correspondence], 1930-1935 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous [Correspondence], January 1936-October 1936 (Box 2)
  - Sponsors - Acceptances
    - A-F (Box 2)
    - G-P (Box 2)
    - Q-Y (Box 2)
  - Sponsors - Refusals (Box 2)
  - Statements [Financial] (Box 2)
  - Subscriptions
    - Duke Power Company, May 1929-October 1930 (Box 2)
    - Duke Power Company, 1931-1936 (Box 2)
    - Duke University (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous
      - January 1929-June 1929 (Box 2)
      - July 1929-December 1929 (Box 2)
      - 1930 (Box 2)
      - 1931-1936 (Box 2)
    - Piedmont and Northern Railway Company (Box 2)
    - Southern Public Utilities Company (Box 2)
    - Subscriptions - Southern Public Utilities Company (Box 2)
  - Suggestions and Estimates for Memorial (Box 2)
  - Oversize Materials (Box 3)
    - Audit Report and Certificate (Box 3)
    - Bank Statements (Box 3)
    - Financial Record Books, [2 volumes] (Box 3)